I've been a journalist now since I was about 17,
أعمل كصحفي منذ أن كنت أبلغ قرابة 17 عاماً،
and it's an interesting industry to be in at the moment,
و هي صناعة مثيرة لكي يعمل بها إنسان هذه الأيام،
because as you all know, there's a huge amount of upheaval
لأنكم كما تعلمون، هناك ثورة كبيرة
going on in media, and most of you probably know this
يشهدها الإعلام، و معظمكم قد يعرف ذلك
from the business angle, which is that the business model
من وجهة نظر تجارية، و هي أن نموذج التجارة
is pretty screwed, and as my grandfather would say,
أصبح سيئا للغاية، و كما يقول جدّي
the profits have all been gobbled up by Google.
استحوذت جوجل على كل الأرباح.
So it's a really interesting time to be a journalist,
كم هو مثير حقاً للإهتمام أن تكون صحفياً في زمننا هذا
but the upheaval that I'm interested in is not on the output side.
لكن الثورة التي تثير اهتمامي ليست ما يتعلق بجانب الإنتاج.
It's on the input side. It's concern with
إنّها تتعلّق بجانب إدخال المعلومات،
how we get information and how we gather the news.
بكيفية الحصول على المعلومة و كيفيّة حصولنا على الأخبار.
And that's changed, because we've had a huge shift
و ذلك قد تغيّر، لأنه أصبح لدينا تغيير هائل
in the balance of power from
في موازين القوة
the news organizations to the audience.
من الشبكات الإخباريّة إلى الجمهور.
And the audience for such a long time was in a position
والجمهور كان لفترة طويلة في وضعية
where they didn't have any way of affecting news
لم يكن لديهم الطريقة للتّأثير على الاخبار
or making any change. They couldn't really connect.
أو لصنع أيّ تغيير. حقيقة لم يكن هناك اتصال على الاطلاق
And that's changed irrevocably.
وهذا قد تغيّر بشكل كبير.
My first connection with the news media was
كان أوّل اتّصال لي بوسائل الاعلام
in 1984, the BBC had a one-day strike.
في عام 1984، كان هناك اضراب بهيئة الاذاعة البريطانية دام يوما واحدا
I wasn't happy. I was angry. I couldn't see my cartoons.
لم أكن سعيدا، كنت غاضبا. لم أتمكّن من قراءة الكرتون
So I wrote a letter.
لذلك كتبت رسالة.
And it's a very effective way of ending your hate mail:
وهي طريقة فعّالة لانهاء رسالة كراهية:
"Love Markham, Aged 4." Still works.
سياسة "مع احترامي. ماركهام، ذات عمر ال4 سنوات" كانت لا تزال فعّالة.
I'm not sure if I had any impact on the one-day strike,
لا أدري إذا ما كان لي أيّ تأثير لايقاف اضراب اليوم الواحد،
but what I do know is that it took them three weeks to get back to me.
لكن ما أعلمه هو أنّ الإجابة على رسالتي استغرقت منهم ثلاثة اسابيع.
And that was the round journey. It took that long for anyone
كانت تلك هي الفترة المعتادة. كان الأمر يستغرق نفس الفترة لأيّ شخص
to have any impact and get some feedback.
للحصول على ردّ أو استجابة.
And that's changed now because, as journalists,
وهذا الأمر تغيّر الآن لأنّنا كصحفيّين،
we interact in real time. We're not in a position
نردّ الفعل في أسرع وقت، لسنا في وضع
where the audience is reacting to news.
يكون للجمهور فيه ردة فعل على الاخبار
We're reacting to the audience, and we're actually relying on them.
نحن الآن نتفاعل مع الجمهور. ونحن في الحقيقة نعتمد عليهم.
They're helping us find the news. They're helping us
هم الذين يساعدونا في ايجاد الاخبار. هم يساعدونا
figure out what is the best angle to take and what is the stuff that they want to hear.
للمعرفة أفضل وجهة نظر لانحياز لها، ومعرفة ما الذي يريدون سماعه.
So it's a real-time thing. It's much quicker. It's happening
فإنّه شيء في قمة السرعة. وهو يحدث
on a constant basis, and the journalist is always playing catch up.
بشكل يومي, والصحفي دائما ما يحاول ملاحقة الموضوع.
To give an example of how we rely on the audience,
لاعطائكم مثال عن كيفية الاعتماد على الجمهور،
on the 5th of September in Costa Rica, an earthquake hit.
في 5 سبتمبر في كوستاريكا، وقع زلزال.
It was a 7.6 magnitude. It was fairly big.
وكانت قوّته 7.6 درجة. لقد كان كبيرا إلى حدّ ما.
And 60 seconds is the amount of time it took
و 60 ثانية كانت هي مقدار الوقت الذي استغرقته
for it to travel 250 kilometers to Managua.
لأن يصل الزّلزال إلى ماناغوا على بعد 250 كيلومترا.
So the ground shook in Managua 60 seconds after it hit the epicenter.
اهتزّت الأرض في ماناغوا 60 ثانية بعد أن ضرب مركز الزلزال.
Thirty seconds later, the first message went onto Twitter,
ثلاثين ثانية بعدها، أوّل رسالة وصلت الى تويتر،
and this was someone saying "temblor," which means earthquake.
كانت رسالة تقول "temblor" أي بمعنى هزة أرضية.
So 60 seconds was how long it took
استغرق الأمر 60 ثانية
for the physical earthquake to travel.
لكي ينتقل الزلزال.
Thirty seconds later news of that earthquake had traveled
ثلاثين ثانية بعدها انتقلت أخبار ذلك الزلزال
all around the world, instantly. Everyone in the world,
لجميع أنحاء العالم، على الفور. كلّ الناس في العالم
hypothetically, had the potential to know that an earthquake
نظريّا، كان بامكانهم معرفة أنّ زلزالا
was happening in Managua.
كان يحدث في ماناغوا.
And that happened because this one person had
وحدث هذا لأنّ شخصا واحدا كانت لديه
a documentary instinct, which was to post a status update,
غريزة وثائقيّة، وهي أن ينشر خبرا
which is what we all do now, so if something happens,
وهذا ما يفعله جميعنا، حتىّ إذا حدث شيئا ما
we put our status update, or we post a photo,
نقوم بتحديث صفحاتنا، أو نقوم بنشر صورة،
we post a video, and it all goes up into the cloud in a constant stream.
نقوم بنشر فيديو، ثمّ تنتشر كلّها بشكل سريع.
And what that means is just constant,
والمعنى هنا هو أنّ هناك
huge volumes of data going up.
أحجام ضخمة من البيانات تنشر.
It's actually staggering. When you look at the numbers,
هذا مذهل فعلا عندما تنظر إلى الأرقام
every minute there are 72 more hours
كل دقيقة هناك 72 ساعة إضافيه من
of video on YouTube.
الفيديوهات على اليوتيوب يتم رفعها.
So that's, every second, more than an hour of video gets uploaded.
كلّ ثانية، يتمّ تحميل أكثر من ساعة من الفيديوهات.
And in photos, Instagram, 58 photos are uploaded to Instagram a second.
بالنّسبة للصّور، فإنّه يتمّ تحميل 58 صورة على موقع انستاغرام كلّ ثانية.
More than three and a half thousand photos go up onto Facebook.
و أكثر من 3 آلاف و 500 صورة تنتشر على الفايسبوك.
So by the time I'm finished talking here, there'll be 864
لذلك، عند قدوم الوقت الذي أنتهي فيه كلامي، سيكون هناك 864 ساعة إضافيّة
more hours of video on Youtube than there were when I started,
تمّت اضافتهاعلى اليوتيوب، أكثر من عدد الفيديوهات التي كانت موجودة بالموقع منذ بداية كلامي اليوم.
and two and a half million more photos on Facebook and Instagram than when I started.
واثنان ونصف مليون صورة تم اضافتها على الفيسبوك وانستاجرام منذ ان بدأت
So it's an interesting position to be in as a journalist,
لذلك فهو موقف مثير للاهتمام أن أكون فيه كصحفي،
because we should have access to everything.
لانّه يجب أن تكون لدينا طريقة للوصول لكل شيء.
Any event that happens anywhere in the world, I should be able to know about it
ويتوجّب عليّ معرفة كل ما يحدث في العالم
pretty much instantaneously, as it happens, for free.
على الفور، عند حدوثه، مجانا.
And that goes for every single person in this room.
وهذا ينطبق على كل الموجودين هنا.
The only problem is, when you have that much information,
المشكلة الوحيدة تقع عند وجود هذا العدد من المعلومات،
you have to find the good stuff, and that can be
عليك ايجاد المعلومات الجيدة، وهذا الامر قد يكون
incredibly difficult when you're dealing with those volumes.
صعبا جدا عندما تتعامل مع هذه الكميّات.
And nowhere was this brought home more than during
وافضل مثال لمثل هذا الامر هو
Hurricane Sandy. So what you had in Hurricane Sandy was
اعصار ساندي. والذي حدث في اعصار ساندي
a superstorm, the likes of which we hadn't seen for a long time,
هي عاصفة لم نر لها مثيلا منذ زمن طويل،
hitting the iPhone capital of the universe -- (Laughter) --
والتي طرقت على عالم الايفون، عاصمة الكون (ضحك)
and you got volumes of media like we'd never seen before.
حينها حصلت على كميات من وسائل الاعلام لم يسبق لها مثيل.
And that meant that journalists had to deal with fakes,
لذلك استوجب على الصحفيين التعامل مع ما هو مزيّف،
so we had to deal with old photos that were being reposted.
لذا تعاملنا مع الصور القديمة التي تمّت إعادة نشرها.
We had to deal with composite images
وتعاملنا مع الصور المركبة
that were merging photos from previous storms.
والصور المدموجة من العواصف السابقة.
We had to deal with images from films like "The Day After Tomorrow." (Laughter)
وصور من الافلام مثل تلك في فلم "بعد غد" (ضحك)
And we had to deal with images that were so realistic
وكان علينا التّصدي الى صور اشبه للواقع
it was nearly difficult to tell if they were real at all.
كان من الصعب جدا تحري اذا ما كانت حقيقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But joking aside, there were images like this one from Instagram
لكن لنتحدّث بجدّية، كان هناك مثل هذه الصور من انستاجرام
which was subjected to a grilling by journalists.
تعرضت لانتقادات شديدة من قبل الصحفيين.
They weren't really sure. It was filtered in Instagram.
لم يكونوا متأكّدين حقا اذا ما تمّ تعديلها على انستاجرام.
The lighting was questioned. Everything was questioned about it.
كان هناك شك في الاضاءة. وكل شئ كان مشكّكا فيه.
And it turned out to be true. It was from Avenue C
و تبيّن أنّ الامر كان صحيحا. كان من شارع "ك"
in downtown Manhattan, which was flooded.
في وسط مانهاتن, التي غمرت بالماء
And the reason that they could tell that it was real
السبب الذي جعلهم يقولون أنّها حقيقية
was because they could get to the source, and in this case,
هو كونهم تمكّنوا من الوصول إلى المصدر، الذي كان في هذه الحالة
these guys were New York food bloggers.
مدونين للطعام بنيويورك.
They were well respected. They were known.
جميعهم حظوا باحترام كبير. لقد كانوا معروفين.
So this one wasn't a debunk, it was actually something that they could prove.
إذن لم تكن هذه خدعة يتمّ كشفها، وإنّما كان هذا شيئا استطاعوا اثباته.
And that was the job of the journalist. It was filtering all this stuff.
هذه هي وظيفة الصحفيين. تصفية كل هذه الامور.
And you were, instead of going and finding the information
وأنت، بدلا من الذهاب لايجاد المعلومات
and bringing it back to the reader, you were holding back
وإعادتها الى القارئ، تحجم
the stuff that was potentially damaging.
الاشياء التي تسبّب الّلف.
And finding the source becomes more and more important --
وايجاد المصدر اصبح أكثر أهمية
finding the good source -- and Twitter is where most journalists now go.
إيجاد مصدر جيد -- وتويتر هو المكان الذي يلجأ اليه الصحفيين الان.
It's like the de facto real-time newswire,
هي مثل وكاله انباء دي فاكتو على ارض الواقع،
if you know how to use it, because there is so much on Twitter.
إذا ما عرفت كيفية استخدامها، لأنّه هناك الكثير في تويتر.
And a good example of how useful it can be
ومثال جيد عن امكانية جعله مفيدا،
but also how difficult was the Egyptian revolution in 2011.
ولكن ايضا مدى صعوبته هي الثورة المصرية في سنة 2011.
As a non-Arabic speaker, as someone who was looking
كشخص لا يتحدّث العربية، وكشخص باحث
from the outside, from Dublin,
من بلد أجنبيّ، من دبلن،
Twitter lists, and lists of good sources,
قوائم تويتر، وقوائم من المصادر الجيدة،
people we could establish were credible, were really important.
من النّاس الذين كان يمكننا ان نتحقق من مصداقيتهم، كانت مهمه جدا.
And how do you build a list like that from scratch?
كيف يمكن بناء قائمة مماثلة من الصفر؟
Well, it can be quite difficult, but you have to know what to look for.
هذا الأمر قد يكون صعبا بعض الشيء، لكن عليك ان تعرف ما الذي تبحث عنه.
This visualization was done by an Italian academic.
هذا التّصور تمّ من قبل اكاديمي ايطالي
He's called André Pannison, and he basically
الذي يدعى أندريه بانيسون، الذي قام
took the Twitter conversation in Tahrir Square
بأخذ حوارات تويتر التي جرت حول ميدان التحرير
on the day that Hosni Mubarak would eventually resign,
في اليوم الذي سيستقيل فيه حسني مبارك،
and the dots you can see are retweets, so when someone
والنقاط التي تراها هي ريتويت، عندما يقوم احدهم
retweets a message, a connection is made between two dots,
بعمل ريتويت لرساله، يتم وصل نقتطين من النّقاط،
and the more times that message is retweeted by other people,
وكلمّا كثر عدد المرات التي يعمل فيها ريتويت للرساله من قبل الاشخاص،
the more you get to see these nodes, these connections being made.
كلما رأيت مثل هذه العقد، هذه الاتصالات تتم.
And it's an amazing way of visualizing the conversation,
إنّها طريقة رائعة لتصور المحادثة،
but what you get is hints at who is more interesting
ولكن ما تحصل عليه هو تلميحات عن من هم أكثر إثارة
and who is worth investigating.
ومن الذي يستحق التحقيق حوله.
And as the conversation grew and grew, it became
ومع نموّ الحديث، أصبح
more and more lively, and eventually you were left
أكثر حيوية، وأخيرا يصبح لديك
with this huge, big, rhythmic pointer of this conversation.
هذا المؤشر الايقاعي الضخم من تلك المحادثة.
You could find the nodes, though, and then you went,
رغم ذلك، ستجد العقود، ثم تذهب
and you go, "Right, I've got to investigate these people.
وتقول لنفسك "اذن عليّ التحقق من أولائك الاشخاص.
These are the ones that are obviously making sense.
هؤلاء يبدو كلامهم أكثر منطقيّة.
Let's see who they are."
دعونا نتعرّف عليهم."
Now in the deluge of information, this is where
في هذا الطوفان من المعلومات, هذا هو المكان
the real-time web gets really interesting for a journalist like myself,
الذي تصبح فيه شبكة الانترنت مثيرة للاهتمام، بالنّسبة لصحفيّ مثلي
because we have more tools than ever
لاننا نملك الان ادوات اكثر من قبل
to do that kind of investigation.
للقيام بذلك النوع من التحقيق
And when you start digging into the sources, you can go
وعندما تبدأ البحث في المصادر، يمكنك الوصول
further and further than you ever could before.
أبعد وأبعد ممّا كان بوسعك من قبل.
Sometimes you come across a piece of content that
أحيانا تجد مجموعة من المحتويات التي تبدو لك
is so compelling, you want to use it, you're dying to use it,
مقنعة تماما، ترغب في استخدامها، وتريد جدا استخدامها
but you're not 100 percent sure if you can because
لكنك لست متأكدا 100% من اذا ما كان بوسعك استخدامها
you don't know if the source is credible.
لأنّك لا تعلم ما إذا كان المصدر جديرا بالثقة.
You don't know if it's a scrape. You don't know if it's a re-upload.
لا تعرف اذا كان المصدر ملعوب عليه. او اذا اُعيد تحميله
And you have to do that investigative work.
وعليك ان تقول بعمل التحري.
And this video, which I'm going to let run through,
وهذا الفيديو, والذي ساشغله الان
was one we discovered a couple of weeks ago.
اكتشفناه منذ بضعة اسابيع
Video: Getting real windy in just a second.
فيديو: تبدأ الرياح خلال ثواني
(Rain and wind sounds)
(صوت المطر والرياح)
(Explosion) Oh, shit!
(انفجار) ياللعنة
Markham Nolan: Okay, so now if you're a news producer, this is something
ماركهام نولان: حسنا، اذا كنت انت منتج أخبار، هذا شيء
you'd love to run with, because obviously, this is gold.
ستحب العمل عليه، لانه يساوي ذهبا.
You know? This is a fantastic reaction from someone,
هل تعلم؟ هذه ردة فعل رائعة من شخص ما،
very genuine video that they've shot in their back garden.
فيديو حقيقي قام بتسجيله في حديقة المنزل.
But how do you find if this person, if it's true, if it's faked,
لكن كيف ستعرف اذا كان هذا حقيقيّا أو مزوّرا،
or if it's something that's old and that's been reposted?
او اذا كان هذا فيديو قديما أو اٌعيد نشره؟
So we set about going to work on this video, and
اذن بدأنا بتعيين العمل على هذا الفيديو،
the only thing that we had to go on was the username on the YouTube account.
و الشيء الوحيد الذي انطلقنا منه هو اسم مستخدم اليوتيوب.
There was only one video posted to that account,
كان هناك فيديو واحد من هذا المستخدم على اليوتيوب
and the username was Rita Krill.
وكان اسم المستخدك "Rita Krill"
And we didn't know if Rita existed or if it was a fake name.
ونحن لا ندري اذا كانت ريتا موجودة فعلا او اذا كان الاسم مزيّفا.
But we started looking, and we used free Internet tools to do so.
وبدأنا بالبحث مستخدمين أدوات مجانية من الانترنت.
The first one was called Spokeo, which allowed us to look for Rita Krills.
أولها تدعى إسبوكيو، والتي ساعدتنا في البحث عن ريتا.
So we looked all over the U.S. We found them in New York,
ثم بحثنا في كل انحاء الولايات المتحدة. فوجدناه في نيويورك،
we found them in Pennsylvania, Nevada and Florida.
ووجدناه في بنسلفانيا ونيفادا و فلوريدا.
So we went and we looked for a second free Internet tool
ثم بحثنا في اداة ثانية مجانيه على الانترنت
called Wolfram Alpha, and we checked the weather reports
تدعى ولفران ألفا، وتتبعنا تقارير الطقس
for the day in which this video had been uploaded,
لليوم الذي تم فيه رفع هذا الفيديو
and when we went through all those various cities,
بعد ان بحثنا من خلال كل هذه المدن
we found that in Florida, there were thunderstorms and rain on the day.
وجدنا انه في نفس ذلك اليوم كانت هناك عواصف رعدية وامطار في فلوريدا
So we went to the white pages, and we found,
لذلك انتقلنا الى دليل الصفحات البيضاء, فوجدنا,
we looked through the Rita Krills in the phonebook,
وبحثنا عن اسم ريتا كريل في دليل الهواتف
and we looked through a couple of different addresses,
نظرنا الى عناوين مختلفة
and that took us to Google Maps, where we found a house.
انتهى بنا الامر الى خرائط Google, حيث وجدنا منزل
And we found a house with a swimming pool that looked
ووحدنا منزل به حوض للسباحة بدى
remarkably like Rita's. So we went back to the video,
يشبه منزل ريتا بشكل كبير. ثم رجعنا الى الفيديو
and we had to look for clues that we could cross-reference.
وبدانا البحث عن ادلة للاستناد عليها
So if you look in the video, there's the big umbrella,
اذن اذا القيت نظرة الى ذلك الفيديو, ستلاحظ وجود مظلة كبيرة
there's a white lilo in the pool,
و ليلو بيضاء في حوض السباحة،
there are some unusually rounded edges in the swimming pool,
وفيه بعض الحواف المدوّرة بشكل غيرعادّي،
and there's two trees in the background.
و هناك شجرتين في الخلفيّة.
And we went back to Google Maps, and we looked a little bit closer,
واستعملنا نظام خرائط جوجل، و نظرنا بأكثر تمعّن،
and sure enough, there's the white lilo,
و تأكّدنا كفاية أنّه كانت هناك ليلو بيضاء،
there are the two trees,
و شجرتين،
there's the umbrella. It's actually folded in this photo.
و هناك المظلّة. لقد تمّ وضعها في الصّورة.
Little bit of trickery. And there are the rounded edges on the swimming pool.
قليلا من التحيّل، و نتحصّل على الحواف المستديرة لحوض السباحة.
So we were able to call Rita, clear the video,
تمكّنا من التصال بريتا، مسح الفيديو،
make sure that it had been shot, and then our clients
التأكّد من عمليّة تصويره، ثمّ كان زبائننا سعداء
were delighted because they were able to run it without being worried.
لأنّهم تمكّنوا من تشغيله دون قلق.
Sometimes the search for truth, though,
لكن البحث عن الحقيقة في بعض الأحيان
is a little bit less flippant, and it has much greater consequences.
قد يكون وقحا قليلا وله عواقب أكبر.
Syria has been really interesting for us, because obviously
سوريا كانت مثيرة للاهتمام بالنّسبة لنا،
a lot of the time you're trying to debunk stuff that can be
لأنّكم تحاولون فضح أمور قد تكون
potentially war crime evidence, so this is where YouTube
أدلّة على جرائم حرب، في مثل هذه الحالات يصبح موقع يوتيوب
actually becomes the most important repository
أهمّ مصدر معلومات
of information about what's going on in the world.
حول الأحداث التي تجري في العالم.
So this video, I'm not going to show you the whole thing,
إذا، هذا الفيديو، سأريكم الأمر برمّته،
because it's quite gruesome, but you'll hear some of the sounds.
لأنّه شنيع جدّا، لكنّكم ستسمعون بعض الأصوات.
This is from Hama.
هذا الفيديو صوّر في مدينة حماة.
Video: (Shouting)
فيديو: (صراخ)
And what this video shows, when you watch the whole thing through,
و ما يكشفه لنا الفيديو، عند مشاهدته كلّه،
is bloody bodies being taken out of a pickup truck
هي جثث دامية يتمّ اخراجها من شاحنة تحميل
and thrown off a bridge.
ثمّ رميها من فوق جسر.
The allegations were that these guys were Muslim Brotherhood
و كانت المزاعم التي تدور هي أنّ هؤلاء الرّجال ينتمون لجماعة الإخوان المسلمين
and they were throwing Syrian Army officers' bodies
و كانوا يقومون برمي جثث ضبّاط الجيش السوري من الجسر،
off the bridge, and they were cursing and using blasphemous language,
و كانوا يشتمون و يستخدمون لغة مسيئة للدبن،
and there were lots of counterclaims about who they were,
و كانت هناك العديد من المعارضة حول هويّة هؤلاء الرّجال،
and whether or not they were what the video said it was.
و ما إذا كانوا بالفعل كما يزعم.
So we talked to some sources in Hama who we had been
لذلك، تحدّثنا مع أحد مصادرنا بحماة، و الذين كنّا
back and forth with on Twitter, and we asked them about this,
على اتّصال معهم عبر موقع تويتر، و سألناهم عن الفيديو،
and the bridge was interesting to us because it was something we could identify.
و الجسر كان مثيرا للاهتمام لنا، لأنّه كان معلما يمكن تمييزه.
Three different sources said three different things about the bridge.
3 مصادر مختلفة قالت 3 أشياء مختلفة حول الجسر.
They said, one, the bridge doesn't exist.
لقد قالوا، أوّلا أنّ الجسر غير موجود.
Another one said the bridge does exist, but it's not in Hama. It's somewhere else.
المصدر الآخر قال بأنّ الجسر موجود بالفعل، لكنّه بمدينو أخرى و ليس بحماة.
And the third one said, "I think the bridge does exist,
مصدرنا الثّالث قال:"أظنّ أنّ الجسر موجود بالفعل،
but the dam upstream of the bridge was closed,
ولكن تمّ إغلاق السدّ بمنبع الجسر،
so the river should actually have been dry, so this doesn't make sense."
لذلك يفترض بالنّهر أن يكون جافّا، لذلك فإنّ الأمر غير منطقيّ."
So that was the only one that gave us a clue.
كان هذا الأخير هو الوحيد الذي مدّنا بدليل.
We looked through the video for other clues.
قمنا بفحص الفيديو للبحث عن أدلّة أخرى.
We saw the distinctive railings, which we could use.
و رأينا الأسوار المميّزة للجسر، و التي تمكّنا من استعمالها.
We looked at the curbs. The curbs were throwing shadows south,
نظرنا إلى الحدود، التي كانت لها ظلال تتّجه نحو الجنوب،
so we could tell the bridge was running east-west across the river.
لذلك استطعنا أن نخمّن أنّ الجسر كان بالجهة الغربية أو الشرقية فوق النّهر.
It had black-and-white curbs.
كان به حدود سوداء و بيضاء.
As we looked at the river itself, you could see there's
عند نظرنا إلى الجسر بعينه، استطعنا رؤية
a concrete stone on the west side. There's a cloud of blood.
صخرة من الخرسانة بالجهة الغربيّة. و سحابة من الدّم.
That's blood in the river. So the river is flowing
كان ذلك دما بالنّهر، إذا فالدّم يطفو
south to north. That's what that tells me.
من الجنوب نحو الشّمال. هذا ما يبدو لي.
And also, as you look away from the bridge,
و أيضا، عند النظر بعيدا عن الجسر،
there's a divot on the left-hand side of the bank,
كان هناك جزء صغير من العشب بالجانب الأيسر من البنك،
and the river narrows.
ثمّ يزداد مجرى النّهر ضيقا.
So onto Google Maps we go, and we start
لذلك، استخدمنا نظام خرائط جوجل
looking through literally every single bridge.
و بدأنا بالتّدقيق في كلّ جسر.
We go to the dam that we talked about, we start just
بدأنا بالسدّ الذي تحدّثت عنه سابقا،
literally going through every time that road crosses the river,
ثمّ تتبّعنا كل جسر يمرّ عبر ذلك النّهر،
crossing off the bridges that don't match.
و نشطب الجسور التي لا تتماشى مع هذه المواصفات.
We're looking for one that crosses east-west.
كنّا نبحث عن جسر يمرّ من الشّرق إلى الغرب.
And we get to Hama. We get all the way from the dam
و بحثنا بمدينة حماة، على طول السدّ
to Hama and there's no bridge.
و لم يكن هناك أيّ جسر.
So we go a bit further. We switch to the satellite view,
لذلك، قرّرنا تغيير طريقة البحث. غيّرنا مجال رؤية القمر الصناعيّ،
and we find another bridge, and everything starts to line up.
و وجدنا جسرا آخر، ثمّ بدأت كلّ الأجزاء تتماشى مع بعضها.
The bridge looks like it's crossing the river east to west.
كان الجسر يبدو كأنّه يمرّ بالنّهر من الشّرق إلى الغرب.
So this could be our bridge. And we zoom right in.
لذلك فهو قد يكون ظالّتنا. قمنا بتكبير الصورة.
We start to see that it's got a median, so it's a two-lane bridge.
و بدأنا نلاحظ احتواءه على خط في المنتصف، لقد كان جسرا ذو مسارين.
And it's got the black-and-white curbs that we saw in the video,
و كما كان به الحدود السوداء والبيضاء التي رأيناها في الفيديو،
and as we click through it, you can see someone's
و عند مزيد البحث، يمكنك أن تلاحظ أنّ أحدهم
uploaded photos to go with the map, which is very handy,
قد قام بتحميل صور تتماشى مع الخريطة، والذي كان أمرا في صالحنا،
so we click into the photos. And the photos start showing us
قمنا بالنّقر على الصّور، و عندما نظرنا إليها،
more detail that we can cross-reference with the video.
اكتشفنا بعض التّفاصيل التي تذكّرنا بما شاهدناه في الفيديو.
The first thing that we see is we see black-and-white curbing,
أوّل ما رأيناه كان الحدود السوداء وا لبيضاء،
which is handy because we've seen that before.
وهو أمر مفيد كوننا رأينا ذلك مسبقا.
We see the distinctive railing that we saw the guys
رأينا السّور المميّز الذي شاهدنا الرّجال
throwing the bodies over.
يقومون برمي الجثث منه.
And we keep going through it until we're certain that this is our bridge.
و واصلنا البحث إلى أن تأكّدنا أنّ هذا هو الجسر الذي نبحث عنه.
So what does that tell me? I've got to go back now
ما الذي نستنتجه من كلّ هذا؟ أعود للكلام
to my three sources and look at what they told me:
الذي قاله لي مصادري الثّلاث:
the one who said the bridge didn't exist,
أحدهم أخبرني أنّ الجسر غير موجود،
the one who said the bridge wasn't in Hama,
الآخر أخبرني أنّ الجسر ليس بمدينة حماة،
and the one guy who said, "Yes, the bridge does exist, but I'm not sure about the water levels."
و الأخير الذي قال لي:"الجسر موجود، لكنّني لست متأكّدا من مستويات المياه تحته."
Number three is looking like the most truthful all of a sudden,
فجأة أصبح مصدرنا الثّالث يبدو أكثر مصداقيّة،
and we've been able to find that out using some free Internet tools
و تمكّننا من معرفة ذلك باستعمال أدوات على الانترنت
sitting in a cubicle in an office in Dublin
بينما كنّا جالسين في حجرة بأحد الكاتب بدبلن
in the space of 20 minutes.
في مدّة زمنيّة لا تتجاوز 20 دقيقة.
And that's part of the joy of this. Although the web
وهذا هو الجزء الممتع من الأمر. رغم أنّ شبكة الانترنت
is running like a torrent, there's so much information there
تشتغل بسرعة شديدة، بها كمّ هائل من المعلومات
that it's incredibly hard to sift and getting harder every day,
التي يصعب فرزها، ويزداد الأمر أكثر صعوبة كلّ يوم،
if you use them intelligently, you can find out incredible information.
لكن إن استخدمتها بطريقة ذكيّة، يمكنك الحصول على معلومات مذهلة.
Given a couple of clues, I could probably find out
بدءا من بعض الأدلة، أستطيع على الأرجح أن أكتشف
a lot of things about most of you in the audience that you might not like me finding out.
العديد من الأمور التي قد لا يريد معظمكم أن أعلم بشأنها.
But what it tells me is that, at a time when
وما أستنتجه من هذا هو أنّه وفي وقت
there's more -- there's a greater abundance of information than there ever has been,
توجد فيه البيانات بوفرة لا مثيل لها سابقا،
it's harder to filter, we have greater tools.
عمليّة الفرز تكون أصعب، لكن لدينا أدوات أفضل.
We have free Internet tools that allow us,
لقد كنّا نستعمل أدوات مجانيّة على الانترنت
help us do this kind of investigation.
التي ساعدتنا على القيام بمثل هذا النّوع من التّحقيق.
We have algorithms that are smarter than ever before,
لدينا خوارزميات أكثر ذكاء من أي وقت مضى،
and computers that are quicker than ever before.
و الحواسيب أسرع الآن من أيّ وقت مضى.
But here's the thing. Algorithms are rules. They're binary.
لكن، الفرق هو أنّ الخوارزميات هي قواعد، وهو ثنائيّة.
They're yes or no, they're black or white.
هناك إمّا نعم أو لا، أسود أو أبيض.
Truth is never binary. Truth is a value.
بينما الحقيقة لا يمكن أن تكون ثنائية. الحقيقة هي قيمة.
Truth is emotional, it's fluid, and above all, it's human.
الحقيقة أمر عاطفيّ، و إنسانيّ.
No matter how quick we get with computers, no matter
مهما تكن سرعة حواسيبنا، مهما تكن
how much information we have, you'll never be able
كميّة البيانات التي نمتلكها، لن تتمكّن أبدا
to remove the human from the truth-seeking exercise,
من حذف النّزعة الإنسانيّة في عمليّة البحث عن الحقيقة،
because in the end, it is a uniquely human trait.
لأنّها في النّهاية سمة فريدة من سمات الإنسان.
Thanks very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا (تصفيق)